I mean, you're just talking about
songwriting, and I would love if you
could break down your songwriting
process. I feel like writing a good song
is like a feeling that you're trying to
catch, and I feel like you know how to
catch it. So, could you explain how you
catch it?
>> So,
I try never to get discouraged. To
answer to answer your question simply, I
try never to get discouraged because
it's okay if a day goes by and nothing
happens. It's okay if a week goes by and
nothing happens. It's okay. I was just
talking to an artist the other day.
They've been sitting in the studio for
30 days, and I'm like, "Are you nervous
that your label's going to get mad at
you that you haven't made anything?" He
was like, "No, it's it's going to come.
It It comes when it comes. We We have to
search constantly for inspiration. We
have to show up for it. It doesn't By By
you all showing up now, this is a big
gallery of inspiration. So, I walked
into
um Do you see this getting progressively
lower?
Just follow it.
I
I heard these chords.
Okay, backstory. I had a friend when I
went to Berkeley. He unfortunately
passed away 2 years prior to me writing
this song, but he always told me
when he was alive that
I would write a song like this, and I
never knew what he meant. He was like,
"One day the music industry's going to
It's going to evolve, and you're going
to be in it." I'm like,
"Sure, whatever you say." His name was
Vale. He always told me that I would
write this song, but he never sang it.
There was no melody or anything like
that. He always just said I was going to
write it. And 2 years later, I walk into
this room with my friend Justin, and
uh he He goes by DJ Frankie. It's he's
what I made this song with, and he Thank
you.
Strong.
I heard these chords. It was like a very
Again, it was 2014. It was a very like
synth out I'm I'm not going to bother
finding a synth here. It was very da
>> [music]
>> And
had the sweeps and all you know white
noise filters
all that stuff and
I was like you know what we're we're
we're adding and building to this track
and it's nothing this is just an example
of my processes it's why don't we just
delete everything we just added sounds
for 2 hours and we still have no song
instead of it being
>> [crying]
>> And the moment I did that I kid you not
I got chills right now the moment I did
that it's it's it's been a
>> [music and singing]
[music]
>> I was singing to my friend and I
realized this was the song that he was
talking about this was the song that he
told me that I would write one day and I
didn't I've just met these co-so I
called they co-producers and songwriters
I'm not going to open up to them like
that so I'm like in the corner like
I'm I and then I find out that DJ
Frankie J Sica Justin is going through
the same thing he lost his friend and
we're just it's like a tennis match
we're just trading lyrics it's been a
long day without you my friend and I'll
tell you all about it when I see you
again we've been we've come a long way
from where I began it's just like it's
like a I feel like I've known this
person for all my life all of a sudden
and then we have we have a completed
chorus and then we spend the entire
night we order Pizza Hut probably a bad
decision we had tummy aches after that
but
then then we then we just continue to
add to it and then
8 months later
after trying a bunch of different
singers on it because again I intended
to come out to LA to to write for other
artists I'm just completely fine being a
demo singer. I ended up I was blessed
enough to be able to stay on the record
with Wiz Khalifa and
I I know that those instances don't
happen every day. Sometimes we have
creative blanks and whatever. I'm I'm
currently in one right now. I just
finished an album and I'm in the car
right over here and I'm like, I don't
know I don't hear any music in my head.
And I used to get kind of bummed out
about it, but now I just let the process
happen. I might go back to the hotel and
turn the shower might make a C sharp.
I I
I know I get on the internet and I kind
of I'm a little theatrical and you know,
things are between us a little
exaggerated at times but because I want
to make it entertaining. I constantly
want people to know that they have it in
them to make music. There's no
you can have a
>> [applause]
>> So that was one example. This is a
really good question. So you know, I'll
I'll I'll have a second to part to it. I
So after the success of that song, we
went to uh
a studio house. They
got this camera, this chef. It was all
fancy all of a sudden and we couldn't
come up with anything because we were so
nervous. They're just spending all this
money. The record label spent all this
money. We were we were nervous that we
weren't going to be able to come up with
anything. So I kind of just
let myself be okay that we might not
come up with anything. And then all of
my
uh co-producers and songwriters at the
time are sitting around the fireplace
and
they come up with this chord progression
and they start singing
>> [music]
>> I didn't write that chorus.
So that was a time where I kind of had
to
like no pride. I didn't write that
chorus, but I will sing that song for
the rest of my life. I lean on the
people who caught the inspiration at the
time and I have no ego about it. I will
sing that song for the rest of my life.
I unified with that song. I relate to
that song heavily. When Christina
Grimmie passed away I
I sang that song. I like felt like I
wrote it.
Music is such an amazing thing
everybody. We're so fortunate to be
here. I hate to be a broken record
but we have such an important
>> [applause]
>> We have such an important role as
such an important role as artists and
producers and songwriters in here in the
day and age where everything is
you know people are having birthday
parties and they're just typing in
you know birthday party music and it's
all artificially made. This is the most
important time to be human right now.
>> [applause and cheering]
[applause]
>> I know that it's probably a little bit
more than what you asked for but that my
the answer is that my in a broad way of
saying my my process varies. One day
I'll you know make the whole track and
write the whole song. One day it'll take
a month. It just patience is key.
I think that's a good answer.
>> [applause]
>> I want to thank you all for coming out
and spending this time with
>> [cheering]